בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is נ"ה, Nun Hey, and
we pick up at the bottom of נ"ד ע"ב. Nun Daled amud
bet. We're going to be sort of shifting from one major section
to another major section of the מסכת masechet without a change of
פרק perek to help us. Anyway, we are dealing with
the last משנה mishna of the discussions relating to idols. As I
said yesterday, I see that there are primarily four sections of this
מסכת: masechet: the one that begins at the opening and goes
till around דף כ"ט, Daf Kaf Tet, the middle of the second
פרק, perek, which is all about interactions with non-Jews before their holidays,
buying and selling different objects and so on.
And then you get from כ"ט Kaf Tet till the end of
the second פרק, perek, which is דף
מ', Daf Mem, and that's like all the stuff about the various
foods of the non-Jews, which includes wine but it's a much broader
discussion. And then you get from the third פרק perek till the
middle of the fourth, which is us, which is all about idols
and objects of worship and objects used in acts of worship and
that you can't derive benefit. And then you're going to get from
what we're going to pick up today from דף נ"ה Daf Nun
Hey till the end, which is all going to be about the
wine of non-Jews. And although we've seen it before, it's going to
get much more specific and technical. Anyway, so
as a closure to all the discussions of idols, we have this
philosophical discussion recorded in the משנה mishna that the philosophers in Rome
asked the רבנים, rabbanim, you know, why doesn't God just get rid
of all the idols? And their answer in the משנה mishna was
like, well, you know, he can't get rid of the sun and
the moon and the stars, and if he were to get rid
of the other stuff, then it would just strengthen the positions of
those who worship the sun, moon, and stars. In the גמרא, Gemara,
it gives a slightly nuanced answer, a different answer about עולם כמנהגו
נוהג, olam k'minhago noheg, which is a very important phrase. The world
just goes in its natural way. Like for some like רמב"ם Rambam
or whatever who believed that God was not so involved in this
world, that was a very important sort of theological principle. And the
גמרא Gemara basically says the world runs
on laws of nature and laws of physics and whatever; it does
not run on laws of morality. So if it did, then somebody
who stole wheat and planted it, the wheat wouldn't grow. But things
don't work that way in this world. God has created a world
that works in a natural type of a way. And therefore God
is not going to meddle in the affairs of human beings, even
though the idols are an affront to God,
and they are going to continue to exist. Okay, so with that,
we pick up on the bottom of נ"ד ע"ב Nun Daled amud
bet and it says like
this: שאל פלוסופוס אחד את רבן גמליאל, Sha'al philosophos echad et Rabban
Gamliel, a certain philosopher asked Rabban Gamliel, כתוב בתורתכם, katuv b'Toratchem, it
says in your Torah, כי ה' אלהיך אש אוכלה הוא אל קנא,
ki Hashem Elokecha esh ochlah hu el kana, God is
a consuming fire, a jealous God. מפני מה מתקנא בעובדיה ואין מתקנא
בה? mipnei mah mitkana b'ovdeha v'ein mitkana bah? Why is God
jealous of those that worship idols but doesn't actually take His anger
out on the idols themselves?
אמר לו, amar lo, so this is not trying to solve the
problem that the way the Torah describes like שכר ועונש s'char v'onesh
and those who worship idols will be punished doesn't exactly seem to
play out in our world. That was maybe a little bit the
question before, although even there it was more of a philosophical question,
not that the promises of the Torah we don't actually always see
playing out. But this is also a question about why, when the
Torah describes God's jealousy, does it speak about God's jealousy burning against
the worshippers of idols? Why isn't it burning against the idols? אמר
לו אמשול לך משל למה הדבר דומה, amar lo emshol l'cha mashal
l'mah hadavar domeh, let me give you a parable, what's it similar
to? למלך בשר ודם שהיה לו בן אחד, l'melech basar vadam shehayah
lo ben echad, so a certain king had a son, והיה אותו
הבן מגדל לו את הכלב, v'hayah oto haben megadel lo et hakelev,
and the son would raise a dog, והעלה לו שם כשם אביו,
v'he'elah lo shem k'shem aviv, and he called the dog by his
father's name. Obviously here God is the king, and a person who
worships idols is attributing divinity or
whatever to some lowly object.
וכשהוא נשבע אומר בחיי כלב אבא, uchshehu nishba omer b'chayei kelev aba,
when he takes an oath, he says, "In the name of the
dog father." So he basically is,
okay, כששמע המלך על מי הוא כועס על הבן הוא כועס או
על הכלב הוא כועס? ksheshama hamelech al mi hu ko'es al haben
hu ko'es o al hakelev hu ko'es? When the king hears, who
does he get angry
at? Does he get mad at the son or at the dog?
הוי אומר על הבן הוא כועס, hevei omer al haben hu ko'es,
you get mad at the son. The son is the one that
did the wrong thing; the dog didn't do anything wrong. Idolaters want
to call silly physical
objects gods; God isn't going to get angry at the objects, he's
going to get angry at the people. The objects didn't do anything
wrong. So אמר לו כלב אתה קורא אותן? amar lo kelev atah
kore otan?
You're calling it a dog? והלא יש בהן ממש. v'halo yesh bahen
mamash. What do you mean? There is some power to it. So
this is very interesting, because רמב"ם Rambam in general, his philosophy, and
he writes this in... his פירוש משניות Perush Mishnayos on this משנה,
Mishna, you know רמב״ם Rambam is very of course adamant that all
this belief in all these gods or whatever is obviously a ton,
all nonsense. And this idea about calling it a dog and saying
they didn't do anything wrong, there's no real powers there, it's just
human beings attributing power to something, works very well with, you know,
רמב״ם's Rambam philosophy. You know, others sort of believe, you know, it's
a problem like, you know, I mean not problem whatever, but the
תורה Torah describes it: God is אלהי האלהים, Elohei HaElohim, God of
the gods, you know, or whatever. So, others read it that, you
know, that the God that, they're, you know, the תורה Torah is
really reflecting a philosophy that God is supreme, but, you know, there
are other powers in the world, maybe God created those other powers
and they're subservient to God or whatever, you know. And so like
the, you know, that's more reflects the simple sense of the פסוקים,
psukim, doesn't go with our sort of, you know, with our more
pure sort of monotheism and so on. But anyway, so this is
seems to be reflecting very consistent with רמב״ם, Rambam, you know, which
is like, oh, there's nothing there, that's just people attributing powers to
other things. So the philosopher said, how could you call it a
dog? It has power. כלבא את קרי לה? הלא יש בה ממש.
Kalba at karei lah? Halo yesh bah mamash. אמר לו מה ראית?
Amar lo mah ra'ita?
What makes you think that these things have any real power, that
it's not just people making stupid mistakes? אמר לו פעם אחת נפלה
דליקה בעירנו ונשרפה כל העיר כולה. Amar lo pa'am achas nafla deleika
be'ireinu venisrefa kol ha'ir kula. So this is actually quite fascinating because
this is exactly what happens, you know, when you get like reports
of believers, right? Everybody who has a belief will tell a story
about how, oh, look, this following thing proves, you know, this amazing
thing happened, and, you know, and it shows that our, you know,
that was our proof that our God is, our belief is the
correct one, our God is true. Beliefs are like that too. Everybody,
everybody who's part of some faith has a story. Oh, what do
you mean of course our תורה Torah is true? Here's this story
and this great רב Rabbi and nothing happened and da-da-da-da-da, right? But
it's like everybody tells a story in every religion. Okay, so that's
what he's saying.
He says, so what happened? There was a fire in our town,
ונשרפה כל העיר כולה, venisrefa kol ha'ir kula, and
the whole town burnt up. ואותו בית עבודה זרה לא נשרף, Ve'oso
beis avoda zara lo nisraf, and that house of idolatry didn't burn,
and that of course, so this clearly proves that there's power to
our God. So he says, אמר לו אמשול לך משל, Amar lo
emshol lecha mashal, let me give you a parable. למה הדבר דומה?
Lemah hadavar domeh? What it's like? למלך בשר ודם שסרחה עליו מדינה,
Lemeilech basar vadam shesarcha alav medina, that a certain country rebelled against
the king. כשהוא עושה מלחמה עם החיים הוא עושה או עם המתים
הוא עושה? Keshehu oseh milchama im hachayim hu oseh o im hameisim
hu oseh? When he goes to war, does he go to war
against the living or against the dead? הוי אומר עם החיים הוא
עושה. Hevei omer im hachayim hu oseh. He does it against the
living. So if there was a fire, okay, rather than sort of
saying it was all just natural events, because if it was natural
events, why did this house, this temple get saved? Okay, so rather
he's saying no, the fire actually was God punishing the people of
the town, maybe for other sins, maybe for worshipping idols, but it's
part of the same point. But God doesn't need to punish the
temple; the temple didn't do anything wrong, it was the people who
did the wrong thing.
Well, but if everything else burns but the temple...
I understand. Anyway, אמר לו, Amar lo, he said to him, אמר
עם החיים... Amar im hachayim... אמר לו כלבא את קורא אותן? מתא
את
קורא אותן? Amar lo kalba at korei osan? Meisa at korei osan?
How
are you making it worse? You're not just calling them a dog,
you're calling him something dead. אם כן יאבדנו מן העולם. Im kein
ye'abdenu min ha'olam. If that's really true, now again it's probably that
as I said yesterday, he's not talking to actual worshippers and believers;
he's talking to philosophers who basically were skeptical of all of this
idolatry and so on. At the same time, you know, they maybe
you could be skeptical and still feel that there's something there, okay?
But that's how come you're able to use these types of terms.
Anyway, he said, if that's really true that it's all such nonsense,
let God wipe it out. אמר לו אילו לדבר שאין העולם צריך
לו היו עובדים הרי הוא מבטלה הרי עובדים לחמה וללבנה ולכוכבים ולמזלות.
Amar lo ilu ledavar she'ein ha'olam tzarich lo hayu ovdim harei hu
mevatlah harei ovdim lachama ulilevana ulikochavim ulimazalos. So this is just like
the end of the משנה. Mishna. You know what, if they had
no use for it God would destroy it. But they worship things
like the sun and the moon and the stars, לאפיקים la'afikim to
like the whatever the wellsprings, ולגאיות uligayos to the mountains. יאבד עולמו
מפני שוטים? Ye'abeid olamo mipnei shotim? Should God therefore destroy His world
because of these idiots? וכן הוא אומר Vichein hu omer and similar
it says, אסף אסף אסף כל מעל פני האדמה, Asof aseif aseif
kol mei'al pnei ha'adama, should I therefore wipe out everything from the
face of the earth, נאום ה׳? ne'um Hashem? אסף אדם ובהמה, Asof
adam uvehema, should I destroy man and beast? אסף עוף השמים ודגי
הים והמכשלות את הרשעים, Asof of hashamayim udegai hayam vehamachshelos es haresha'im,
the birds of the heaven and the fish of the sea,
all the things that cause wicked people to stray. If I would
destroy everything they cause wicked people to stray, I'd wind up destroying
the whole world. ומפני שהרשעים נכשלים בהן יאבדם מן העולם? Umipnei sheharesha'im
nichshalim bahen ye'abdeim min ha'olam?
Do you think just because the wicked stumble on them God should
destroy them from the world? ולאדם הן עובדין Velo'adam hein ovdin and
you know, they even worship people. ואכרתי את האדם מעל פני האדמה?
Ve'ichratti es ha'adam mei'al pnei ha'adama? Do you therefore want me to
destroy human beings from the earth? Okay, so therefore God doesn't destroy
it because there's no need. Okay, so not no need, because
it would just be too much. שאל אגריפס שר צבא את רבן
גמליאל. Sha'al Agrippas sar tzava es Rabban Gamliel. So Agrippas
the head of the Roman army or whatever- who knows?
No. כתוב בתורתכם, Kasuv beSorasechem, it's written in your תורה, Torah,
כי ה׳ אלוהיך
אש אוכלה הוא אל קנא. Ki Hashem Elohecha eish ochlah hu Eil
kanna.
Hashem your God is a consuming fire, a jealous God. כלום מתקנא
אלא חכם בחכם וגיבור בגיבור ועשיר בעשיר? Klūm miskanneh ella chacham bechacham
vegibor begibor ve'ashir be'ashir? Is there any jealousy but of a wise
man in a wise man, a hero in a hero, and a
rich man in a rich man? What does God have to be
jealous of if these things are really nonsense, right? Do you get
a does a wise person only gets jealous of another wise person,
who wants to prove who's the the best you know who's the
best or a valorous with another or rich with a rich? They
don't get jealous of somebody you know who's lesser than them. So
clearly this shows that these gods have some power. אמר לו, Amar
lo, he said to him, אמשול לך משל. Emshol lecha mashal. Let
me give you a parable. למה הדבר דומה, Lema hadavar domeh, what's
it like? לאדם שנשא אשה על אשתו. Leadam shenasa isha al ishto.
So a man marries a wife you know after his first wife.
So חשובה ממנה אין מתקנא בה. Chashuva mimena ein mitkaneh bah. So
if the second wife is of a higher social status than the
first wife doesn't get so jealous like yeah I wouldn't count on
it. רש"י Rashi sort of says רש"י Rashi some people add in
רש"י, Rashi, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, אין מתקנא בה, ein
mitkaneh bah, the first narrow line, את אשתו ראשונה אינה מקפדת et
ishto rishona einah makpedet
and some people put in the words כל כך kol kach לשנוא
את בעלה. lisno et ba'ala. Okay,
so maybe you do get angry but it's not as offensive. You
understand if you're marrying somebody of higher status, right? When does the
wife get upset? When the guy marries his you know bimbo secretary
or whatever you know and that that's really what's offensive. I'm sorry
that's probably a sexist term. Okay, we gotta edit that one out.
Okay anyway, I'm sorry. Okay, חטאתי העויתי. Chatati aviti. Alright
anyway. Yeah, alright anyway. חשובה ממנה אין מתקנא בה. chashuva mimena ein
mitkaneh bah. פחותה ממנה מתקנא בה Pichuta mimena mitkaneh bah
when he marries somebody of lower social status, somebody who's you know
who's beneath her, then then she feels you know all that more
sort of like you know
betrayed and offended. So if you know you're just סתם stam a
physicist and you're looking around in the world then you're only jealous
of the person who's almost as good of a physicist as you.
You're not jealous about the I don't know the movie star or
the basketball player whatever you know they're not relevant to you. But
here it's not that God סתם stam is jealous of the other
gods. God isn't but what God gets angry about and you know
is offended by is the fact that we give our fidelity
to those other gods and that's even a greater offense to God
that we give our fidelity to those things that are that are
that are meaningless. Now still nevertheless even though it says that you
know פחותה ממנה pichuta mimena it still sounds like it's sort of
in the same ballpark. You know what I mean? Or that maybe
like like it still sounds like those gods are not just completely
imagined things. They're something. They might be something much you know much
trivial or whatever you know but still not completely like it said
before like it was completely imagined. So there's a slightly different I
think subtext here, yes.
But anyways I was just looking at the verses in צפניה Tzefanya
that we just had on the very top of the עמוד. amud.
The גמרא Gemara is taking it rhetorically right we were just like
oh boy. Correct. But you know the way it's translated here that
this is what God will do if you look at the verses
ונתתי ידי על יהודה ועל כל יושבי ירושלים והכרתי מן המקום הזה
את שאר הבעל. Venatati yadi al Yehuda veal kol yoshvei Yerushalayim vehichratti
min hamakom hazeh et shear habaal. It's all of the things that
God is going to do not that God won't do he will
do.
Right. Okay. Yes, the גמרא Gemara doesn't always read the פסוקים psukim
כפשוטו. kipshuto. Alright moving on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר ליה זונין לרבי עקיבא. Amar lei Zunin leRabbi Akiva. Now זונין
Zunin who you might know there was a בית זונין Beis Zunin
who appears a lot so this is apparently a Jew, okay? Maybe
a wealthy Jew or something. Anyway he said to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, ליבי ולבך ידוע, Libi ulevacha yadoa, דעבודת כוכבים לית בה ממשא.
davodas kochavim leis bah mamasha. You and I know that this stuff
is nonsense. But I have a question. Here's a good Jew not
just a philosopher, right? None of these conversations could happen with the
actual worshippers. They could happen with the non-Jewish philosophers, they could happen
among the Jews. You're not going to say you know these types
of of things to the actual believers especially if they have the
power over you. Anyway so he said to him, you and I
know דעבודת כוכבים לית בה ממשא davodas kochavim leis bah mamasha this
stuff has no substance. והא קחזינן גבי דאזלי כי מתיברי ואתו כי
מיתרמי, Veha kachazinan gavi deazli ki mityavrei ve'asu ki mitramyei, but we
see people that go into their these these houses of worship and
they go in when they are like you know with when they're
ill and they and they come out and they're healed. Okay or
they go in there lame and they come out where they're healed
you know like they have these revival tents or whatever you know
and somebody they do something and if somebody it's like seems to
have a miraculous recovery right these are questions you ask like how
does that work if I they really I don't believe in it
but what how do you explain that phenomenon? Okay. So מאי טעמא,
Mai ta'ama, why why does that happen? אמר לו אמשול לך משל.
Amar lo emshol lecha mashal. Let me give you a parable. למה
הדבר דומה, Lema hadavar domeh, what's it like? לאדם נאמן שהיה בעיר
וכל בני עירו היו מפקידים אצלו שלא בעדים. Leadam ne'eman shehaya be'ir
vechol bnei iro hayu mafkidim etzlo shelo be'edim. There was a very
trustworthy person in the city and everybody in the city gave him
objects you know gave him objects to watch and they didn't even
bother with having witnesses cause he was so trustworthy they knew that
they didn't need any evidence you know any to be able to
back up the fact that
they had entrusted their objects with him.
ובא אדם אחד והפקיד אצלו בעדים. Uva adam echad vehifkid etzlo be'edim.
And one person decided was not trustworthy did not trust him and
decided to use witnesses. ופעם אחת שכח והפקיד אצלו שלא בעדים. Ufa'am
achat shachach vehifkid etzlo shelo be'edim. And one time this guy who
would always use witnesses had him watch his objects without witnesses. אמרה
לו אשתו, Amrah lo ishto, so the wife of the person who
would who the trustworthy person, the person who would watch all the
objects, said to him, בוא ונכפרנו, Bo venichparenu, let's go
and deny him that we have his object just to show him.
right. Like everybody else of course you're trustworthy and you return it,
you don't need witnesses. This guy who didn't trust you, let's, it'll
serve him right, deny that you have his object. אמר לה Amar
lah he said to her וכי מפני ששוטה זה עשה שלא כהוגן
vechi mipnei sheshoteh zeh asah shelo kehogen because this idiot acted improperly,
you know, he decided to not trust me even though I'm a
trustworthy person.
So אנו נאבד אמונתנו anu neabed emunateinu should we therefore lose our
trustworthiness? You know, people will hear that we've denied something. So we
have to do the right thing even if this guy's acting like
an idiot. Okay. אף כך af kach so what's the משל, mashal,
what's the נמשל? nimshal? אף כך, af kach, ייסורין בשעה שמשגרין אותם
על אדם yisurin beshaah shemeshagrin otam al adam when God sends afflictions
to to people, משביעין אותם mashbiin otam and God make these afflictions
take an oath שלא תלכו אלא ביום פלוני shelo telchu ela beyom
ploni that they should only leave this person on such and such
a day, okay, ולא תצאו אלא ביום פלוני, velo tetzu ela beyom
ploni, ובשעה פלונית uvshaah plonit on such an hour, ועל ידי פלוני
veal yedei ploni when you know with such when a certain person
sort of attends to them, ועל ידי סם פלוני veal yedei sam
ploni or what a certain medicine attends to them, meaning we would
explain this not as a שבועה, shvuah, we would just say, you
know, people have natural afflictions and sometimes they'll get healed, you know,
and that's and it'll be circumstantial that if that time intersects with
the time when they're going to this church or to this, you
know, house of worship or whatever it is. כיון שהגיע זמנם לצאת
keivan shehigia zmanam latzet when that time happened, הלך זה לבית עבודה
זרה halach zeh leveit avodah zarah this guy happens to go to
a to a house of idol worship. אמרו ייסורין amru yisurin so
the afflictions say to themselves, the afflictions are now the trustworthy person
and their wife
and their wife. So דין הוא שלא נצא din hu shelo netze
you know, we shouldn't because this guy's now going to this house
of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, we should just stay on this person
and continue to afflict him and not go back to where we
were sent from. וחוזרים ואומרים vechozrim veomrim and then they say back,
וחוזרים ואומרים vechozrim veomrim excuse me, and then they go back and
say, וכי מפני ששוטה זה עשה שלא כהוגן אנו נאבד שבועתנו vechi
mipnei sheshoteh zeh asah shelo kehogen anu neabed shvuateinu
because this guy's acting like an idiot, should we therefore not satisfy
our oath? We have taken an oath that we would leave this
person at such and such a time. So the way you would
sort of say is is that like like, okay, the circumstances are
that this guy got better and it happened to intersect with when
he went to this house of worship. There's a lot of people
go to the house of worship and don't get better. This is
so totally true, you know, in terms of this issue of like
confirmation bias, right? I don't know if it's exactly so, you know,
so a lot of people can pray, you know, there's a they
tell a story about this guy, I mean, not in an עבודה
זרה avodah zarah context, about this guy that people would go to,
you know, they all they thought he had influence with the Russian
government. This was, you know, when the Russians would conscript, you know,
Jewish kids for like 20 years into the service, the Czar's government.
So they went to this guy and people would give him like
a lot of money to try to talk to the, you know,
to the Russian government to get the kids out of the army
service. And you know, sometimes the kids would get out and sometimes
not. So anyway, finally somebody said to him, he said like, I
don't understand like, you know, who do you know, what's your influence?
He says, I don't know anybody. Sometimes they get out, sometimes they
don't, you know, they give me the money and they assume it's
because of something I did. So you know, it's the same type
of thing, right? You know, I mean that happens, you know, people
will go and they'll pray to this statue or whatever for a
רפואה. refuah. They'll go to I mean it happens today, they go
to מירון, Meron, they pray for a שידוך shidduch or whatever it
might be, right? Let's, by random chance it happens,
I don't know, five percent of the time, ten percent of the
time, and those are the stories you hear, and you don't hear
the other ninety percent of the stories, right? So God doesn't always
answer, the gods don't, you know, whatever, doesn't always work, but the
time it works, that's the proof. That seems to be the גמרא's
Gemara's point. Okay. עולם כמנהגו נוהג. olam keminhago noheg. Right? Exactly. This
is just people will attribute things and they'll whatever, but that doesn't
prove anything. Okay. והיינו דאמר רבי יוחנן vehayinu deamar Rabi Yochanan and
that's what רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan says, מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv what's
meant by the verse, וחלים רעים ונאמנים? vecholim raim veneemanim? Okay, it
says, you know, evil and trustworthy afflictions, רעים בשליחותם raim bishlichutam
they're evil in their because they satisfy what they've been sent to
do is to bring affliction onto people, ונאמנים בשבועתם veneemanim bishvuatam they're
trustworthy in their oath, they take an oath that they will leave
at a certain time. אמר ליה רבא בר רב יצחק לרב יהודה
amar leh Rava bar Rav Yitzchak leRav Yehudah האיכא בית עבודה זרה
באתראן haika beit avodah zarah be'atran one minute, but there's a house
of idolatry in our place, דכי מצטריך עלמא למיטרא dechi mitztarich alma
lemitra when people need rain, מתחזי להו בחלמא mitchazi lehu bechalma
their god appears to them in a dream, ואמר להו שחטו לי
גברא veamar lehu shachtu li gavra oh, this is horrific, slaughter for
me a person, human sacrifice, ואייתי מיטרא veaiti mitra and
and rain will come. Now, I don't really understand this because this
is in בבל Bavel and in בבל Bavel I didn't know, you
know, Zoroastrianism, I didn't know anything about human sacrifice, so I don't
know what the historical context is. But anyway, he says, שחטו ליה
גברא ואתי מיטרא shachtu leh gavra veati mitra and it works! Okay,
so how do you explain that? אמר ליה השתא אי הוי שכיבנא
לא אמרי לכו האי מילתא amar leh hashta ei hava shchivna lo
amri lechu hai milta you know what, if I had just died
before today, I wouldn't have had a chance to tell you this
important teaching. What's this important teaching? דאמר רב מאי דכתיב deamar Rav
mai dechtiv what's meant by the verse אשר חלק ה׳ אלהיך אותם
לכל העמים asher chalak Hashem Elokecha otam lechol haamim God has divided
them, you know, the stars and the and the whatever to all
the nations תחת כל השמים. tachat kol hashamayim. So it, you know,
it's sort of like it, so it's, that's an interesting פסוק pasuk
because it goes against sort of the sense of, you know, שבע
מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvot bnei Noach is is one is the
big one is a big one is עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. עבודה
זרה avoda zara and the פסוק pasuk sort of speaks about you
will stray after the stars and the heavens etc. which God has
distributed for the for the non-Jews under the heavens where it sounds
like God is saying let them worship the stars like he doesn't
have a problem with them worshipping stars. Anyway, so here it's using
the פסוק pasuk to actually say not that God sort of is
okay with it, but God has given people a basis to err.
And you want to err, there's things that can lead you astray.
ומלמד שהחליקן בדברים
u'melamed she'chechlikan bi'dvarim one minute, well, right, that's your test, that's your
נסיון. nisayon.
So אשר חלק, asher chalak, it's a play on the word חלק,
chalak, שהחליקן בדברים she'chechlikan bi'dvarim God sort of has seduced them with
words כדי לטורדן מן העולם kedei le'tordan min ha'olam in order to
make them, you know, destroy them from the world. So God maybe
put powers in this world and put things in this world that
if you want to stray after them you can stray after them.
So that's a little bit different than everything that we've said until
now. Until now we've...
Doesn't he answer the question like that too? Like you know, why
that temple didn't burn down?
Right, that would be the answer to everything. You know, oh God
has given us basis, you know, you know God does that to
test us, right, which is also the answer to everything that goes
against your faith. God is just testing us. Okay, והיינו דאמר ריש
לקיש v'hainu d'amar Reish Lakish and that's also called something, that's what's
called, that's called not, that's the other thing, it's called what's it
called, cognitive dissonance, right? When the things sort of don't, you know,
it's all just a test, God whatever, anyway, okay. והיינו דאמר ריש
לקיש v'hainu d'amar Reish Lakish מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv what's meant by
the verse, אם ללצים הוא יליץ ולענוים יתן חן im la'letzim hu
yalitz v'la'anavim yitein chen if to the mockers God will mock and
to the humble God will give, kindness whatever, anyway, favor. בא לטמא
פותחין לו, ba l'tamei potchin lo, if somebody wants to become טמא,
tamei, you know, there's enough things that you can sort of seize
onto that can lead you astray. ובא לטהר מסייעין אותו u'ba l'taher
mesayin oso or somebody wants to go on the right purpose God
will you know things will come to help support that person in
his path. So that actually is the one answer that sort of
allows you to deal with all these problems. God has put these
things in the world, you know, God has sort of created the
world 5,700 whatever years ago but put all the dinosaur bones in
there to begin with, you know. So God has put all these
things in the world, so to give people a basis to go
astray if they want to go astray. Okay, anyway, the best answers
I think were the ones about what do you call it, about
עולם כמנהגו נוהג, olam k'minhago noheig, but then you have to explain
claims that seem to be, you know, brought as evidence to one
to a certain type of a faith, which the גמרא Gemara actually
did, you know, in terms of things like confirmation bias and so
on. Okay, so that really was a nice little philosophical conclusion of
that section. That was like, I would say, the, as I said,
the third major section. One about transactions with non-Jews, interacting with the
larger world, one about foods and one about the actual idols. And
now I have no idea why these things, the transition points are
in the middle of a פרק. perek. Maybe Avi Walfish could tell
us, he's a big scholar of משנה Mishnah and he very much
believes at the, sort of at the literary construct of the משניות
Mishnayos and of the פרקים. perakim. So I never understand like why
some of these things transition in the middle of a פרק. perek.
But anyway, but now we get to what I think is the
major final section which I have to tell you, I think this
section we just did was probably like the most fun, you know.
It was like interesting, thinking about עבודה זרה avoda zara and idols
and the real, anyway, but anyway, but here we get to a
lot of details about יין נסך yayin nesech and סתם יינם stam
yeinam which are very, very relevant, but they will, some of them
get to be a little bit technical. Right, seems like we had
a bunch of this list. We had well, it was a little,
we had יין yayin mentioned in a list of a lot of
stuff that were forbidden to eat, but now we're really honing in
on it. Okay. לוקחין גת בעוטה מן העובדי כוכבים lokchin gas be'uta
min ha'ovdei kochavim אף על פי שנוטל בידו ונותן לתפוח. af al
pi she'notel b'yado v'nosein la'tapuach. So you take a, now I'm sure
I meant to look this up, I didn't, I bet some of
you in here will know this better than me, but basically the
way it works, right, I mean I don't know if you've ever
seen these things in Israel, right,
they've got these huge millstones,
right, and like these whatever and they put, I forget how they
sort of screw it on top or whatever. Anyway, and they put
all the grapes down here, right, and then they lower down this
millstone, or maybe it's a bar? Is it a bar or something?
I think it's a bar, right? That's the קורה, kora, right, actually
that's the קורה, kora, right, exactly. Anyway, now it's a bar. Okay.
Anyway, okay, and that sits on it and you know, the weight
whatever, you know, slowly takes gets the oil out. Oh that's, oh
no, that's for, that's for olives, right? Is that, that's not the
same. There's olives and there's grapes, I'm sorry, see I don't even
know what the heck I'm talking about. Anyway, it doesn't matter. The
basic point is is that there's a period where you got the
grapes, okay, and this is your גת, gas, okay, like Goliath of
גת. gas. Okay, anyway,
you got your grapes and you stomp them or you press them
or you do something, right? It's because the olives need to be
pressed very slowly. Okay. And you got this, okay, and then you
start getting the oil to come out. And then apparently what you
do, again it's one of those English translations has a better explanation,
this will be like, so it's starting, your juice is starting to
come out here. Then you go ahead, so that's step number one,
and then you go ahead, here you are in step number two
and you carry all of it, you got a super long arm,
maybe in a כלי, kli, you pour... And then you go ahead,
here you are on step number two, and you carry all of
it,
you got a super long arm, maybe in a כלי, kli, you
put it, you carry it, you put it into something like this,
okay,
and then it's going to go down to a בור bor here.
See this is like גמרא Gemara drawing 101. Anyway,
so you lower it here like here, you put it here, okay,
and then as the wine comes out it goes out here and
it goes into here, and this is the בור. bor. And then
he says you know the line in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, בור
סיד שאינו מאבד טיפה, bor sud she'eino me'abeid tipah,
because sometimes they would plaster this with, you know, with plaster in
order so that it would retain all the wine, at this stage
it's like grape juice. Okay,
so that's basically what you've got. So I guess here what flows
out of this stuff, right? I think this is roughly correct. If
one of your English translations makes it more accurate than this you
can let me know. Okay, alright. So anyway, דורכין גת עם העובדי
כוכבים. dorchin gat im ha'ovdei kochavim. Okay,
so you this is the גת gat with the עובד כוכבים, oved
kochavim, so it's now been like trampled on and there's juice that's
there. The question is at what stage does this become considered wine,
okay, in order that a non-Jew touching it will make it a
problem? That's the basic question. When is it wine? So the non-Jew
did this, he trampled it. There's all this grape juice mixed up
with all these grapes, but
it hasn't really come out, right? So you can purchase this and
it's not yet wine, even though the non-Jew trampled the grapes. Okay.
דורכין גת עם העובדי כוכבים אף על פי שנוטל בידו ונותן לתפוח,
dorchin gat im ha'ovdei kochavim af al pi she-notel beyado venoten latapuach,
you're going to take them from here and put them on this,
this is called the תפוח, tapuach, okay, like an apple, like it's
a mound. Okay, you're going to move this stuff, okay, ואינו עושה
יין נסך עד שירד לבור, ve'eino oseh yayin nesech ad she-yered labor,
and this stuff does not have a status of יין נסך yayin
nesech until it gets down here. So even though there's juice here
and you move it or whatever, it's not going to be יין
נסך yayin nesech until it gets down.
Wait, what does that mean that everything, it just means the stuff
in the בור bor then, right?
Or does it mean everything? This stuff is יין נסך. yayin nesech.
It sounds like even this is not יין נסך. yayin nesech. Right,
correct. That is correct, that's what it sounds like. Okay. ירד לבור
מה שבבור אסור והשאר מותר. yared labor mah she-ba-bor assur vehashear mutar.
Once it's here, this is okay, but don't think that because this
now is defined as wine, that automatically makes all of this defined
as wine. No, this remains okay. So there's a long תוספות Tosafot
that discusses this, okay, and there's like three actual possibilities here, whatever,
that the תוספות Tosafot deals with. One is like what it sounds
like is, and this is the way רש"י Rashi reads it, that
even if a non-Jew is still touching this over here, okay, and
certainly if he's touching this, it's okay. The only even after it's
gone down into the בור, bor, the only thing that's forbidden is
the stuff that has a status of יין yayin is the stuff
in the בור. bor. Okay. תוספות Tosafot suggests the possibility that once
there's stuff in the בור, bor, then everything here is considered to
be יין, yayin, but the simple sense is no. Even once it's
in the בור, bor, only the stuff in
the בור bor is יין, yayin, this stuff is not. The other
חידוש chiddush is, and there's going to be a part of a
discussion, you know, that you get in general by סתם יינם, stam
yeinam, which is the question about ניצוק. nitzok. Okay? If somebody is
here pouring something, okay, you know,
and here's a, he's pouring wine from, I don't know what that
is, but anyway he's pouring wine from one vessel into the next,
okay, and a non-Jew touches this wine, does because it's connected through
a flow make the stuff up here even forbidden?
But even if it does normally, it doesn't here, because here the
idea is only this is considered wine. At this stage, it's still
pressed grapes in the process or whatever it is. Only this is
considered wine, so the stuff up here is okay even if he
directly touched it. Okay. So that's basically the way תוספות Tosafot explains
it. The רשב"ם Rashbam has a stricter read and he says this
is forbidden even if it wasn't touched. Why? Because
if a non-Jew, assuming a non-Jew is pressing it here, okay, so
if the non-Jew here, since the non-Jew's act caused the wine to
go down and caused it to go in here, so that's an
idea that that's considered like he touched it and we're going to
get to issues of indirect touch. Okay, that's the way the רשב"ם
Rashbam explains it, but it says והשאר מותר vehashear mutar
though, it says מה שבבור אסור.
mah she-ba-bor assur. No, so this is forbidden, but this is forbidden
even without being touched. It's forbidden because the power, the energy of
the non-Jew caused it to move. But that's not the פשט. pshat.
Anyway, תוספות Tosafot basically rejects this, okay. For רש"י Rashi and תוספות,
Tosafot, other than this one explanation of the רשב"ם, Rashbam, we'll get
to כוחו kocho later, it's only this and only if you touch
this and the rest remains totally okay. That's the simple read of
the משנה. mishnah. Okay, alright. So now
where were we? Okay.
I'm just checking if there's something in תוספות Tosafot I wanted to
bring out. Okay, okay. דורכין עם העובד כוכבים בגת. dorchin im ha'oved
kochavim begat.
Now we turn to... Something that is very important, not even so
much about יין, yayin, because this, this is very important in terms
of יין, yayin, at what stage is it considered to be סתם
יינם stam yeinam or יין yayin whatever, wine in order that it
could become סתם יינם stam yeinam or יין נסך. yayin nesech. This
next part is a very important in terms of general discussion of
the- of a new idea called אסור לסייע לידי עוברי עבירה. assur
lesayea l'yadei ovrei aveira.
We've had earlier the idea of לפני עור. lifnei iver. לפני עור
lifnei iver is giving you an object that you don't have access
to and therefore you're going to sin with this object. I give
you a טרף treif piece of meat. I give you something that
you're going to use towards your עבודה זרה avoda zara or something
like that. Okay, and then even if you did have access to
it, maybe it would be a דרבנן derabbanan of לפני עור. lifnei
iver. מסייעין לידי עוברי עבירה mesayin l'yadei ovrei aveira is you're already
doing your עבירה, aveira, but I'm going to join in and help
you with it. Okay, so let's take a look. This is going
to be- so this is not limited to a יין נסך, yayin
nesech, although the context here is יין נסך. yayin nesech. דורכין עם
עובדי כוכבים בגת, dorchin im ovdei kochavim begat, you can go ahead
and trample grapes with the non-Jew in the גת gat when you're
over here, here's where you're trampling. Okay, here you have it,
this big funnel, trampling the grapes. Okay, by the way, since we're
talking about- about, here's your feet, you're trampling that. Anyway, you know,
I think I've mentioned this before, the whole idea that רש"י Rashi
was a vintner comes from the fact that in one letter רש"י
Rashi says,
I have to end this letter now because it's time to go
stamp the grapes. He's a משגיח? mashgiach? So from there we assume
that רש"י Rashi was a vintner, but חיים סולובייצ'יק Chaim Soloveitchik says
anybody who knows anything about wine making in France understands that there's
only like two weeks to stamp the grapes and everybody in the
town was part of it and he basically says it's like if
it was ערב פסח erev Pesach and רש"י Rashi had written, I
have to leave now because I have to go bake the מצה,
matzah, we would have assumed רש"י Rashi was a baker. So anyway,
alright, so here you are,
you're stomping with the non-Jew. Why are you allowed to do it?
Well, since we've established that it's not yet considered יין, yayin, it's
not yet אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, so you're allowed to do it
and you're allowed to get paid for it. And you're not allowed
to get paid rabbinically, okay, let's say, you know,
to work with things that are אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Even though
you could say you're not directly getting הנאה hana'ah from the wine,
you're getting הנאה hana'ah from the fact, you know, because you're working
and you're being paid for your work or whatever, but okay,
you're not allowed to get- to, you know, to earn money and
to do work and get paid for work you do with things
that are אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. That we'll see later. But at
this stage, it's not אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah yet, it's only going
to get אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah later. So that's why you're allowed
to work with him and get paid. Now, there's another issue.
It means you couldn't help bottle that stuff?
You couldn't be paid, right. If it was a non-Jew you couldn't
be paid to do bottling this wine. But this you can be
paid to do, okay, because it's not yet wine. Now there's another
issue. The other issue is that this משנה mishna assumes that you
cannot cause טומאה tumah
to stuff in ארץ ישראל, eretz yisrael, to טהרות. taharot. Okay, so
to things that are טהור, tahor, even if they're not yet תרומה
terumah or other types of things. And a non-Jew- they'd be anywhere?
Anywhere? Well, no, but it's specifically about ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael because
it would relate to the תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot even though it's
טבל tevel or the same. Anyway, the non-Jew is considered טמא. tamei.
Okay, so he's doing it and he's making it טמא. tamei. So
why are you allowed to participate in it? Well, because once he
did- he began and you're only joining in after he began, it's
already טמא. tamei. So you didn't make it טמא. tamei. Okay, so
that's
okay.
And you don't become טמא tamei by the way by doing it.
And we'll see in a minute how it'll be different in a
minute with a Jew. אבל לא בוצרין aval lo botzrin what you
cannot do is go ahead and take the grapes from the vine.
Why can you not go ahead and pick the grapes from the
vine with him? Because at this stage the grapes are not yet
טמא. tamei. So if you are going to pick the grapes, you
are actually going to be participating in a process that's going to
end with them becoming טמא. tamei. So you're helping make them טמא.
tamei. You're being גורם טומאה. gorem tumah. So it's actually interesting. Here
they're already טמא, tamei, it's a matter of the past. You're not
doing anything, but here they're טהור. tahor. So to do it and
knowing they're going to end up here, it's considered to be גורם
טומאה gorem tumah and you're not allowed to be גורם gorem to
them.
So if you're going to sell those grapes in the market.
גורם טומאה, gorem tumah, what? Yeah, if you were to sell them-
why? Because you mean they wouldn't be- because it wouldn't be
to someone who's eating, yeah, someone's eating grapes, right? You're selling it
to, you know,
what does that have to do with it?
Then you can pick them, right? They're not going to become טמא
tamei then.
If you weren't going to stomp them with the non-Jew, yeah. Okay,
but it's because they're headed this way. So you're not allowed to
do that, that's גורם טומאה. gorem tumah. This you're allowed to do.
Why? Because they're already טמא. tamei.
Number one. And number two, because it is not yet יין. yayin.
Okay, so this you can do, that you can't do.
Why do we care if we create טומאה? tumah?
Why do we care if what?
I always thought טומאה tumah was a matter of can you eat
it, can't you eat it, but is there a problem- I mean,
I assume there's- why is there a problem of creating more טומאה
tumah in the world?
Yeah, it seems like, I mean it's true, later the גמרא Gemara
will sort of discuss the unique aspects about stuff that's חייב chayav
in תרומות trumos and מעשרות, ma'asros, but this actually is owned by
a non-Jew and a non-Jew's produce is not חייב chayav in תרומות
trumos and מעשרות, ma'asros, then it seems that it's not based on
that and the emphasis is טומאה בארץ ישראל. tumah b'eretz yisrael. So
it seems like you're right, there's a problem according to this approach
of bringing טומאה tumah into Israel even if it doesn't have an
effect on תרומות trumos and מעשרות. ma'asros. Okay, and in the end
the גמרא Gemara is going to have a ברייתא braita that rejects
that. But you don't have to ask why, right? In other words,
if he's saying I want to hire you to... Okay, but if
you know... No, no, I'm just saying like you don't have to
say like oh wait, is it for... I don't know, it's an
interesting question if you have a ספק. safek. Okay, okay, but that
you could be מברר. mivahrer. ישראל שעושה בטומאה. yisrael she'oseh b'tumah. Now
let's say it's a Jew who's also, you know, doing this whole,
who's stomping the grapes and he owns the vineyard, and but you
know he's going to do it בטומאה. b'tumah. So there it's the
reverse. I mean not the reverse, excuse me, לא דורכין ולא בוצרים
עמו. lo dorkhin v'lo bortzim imo. You cannot do either this בוצרים.
botzrim. Why can't you do the בוצרים? botzrim? Obviously because it's גרם
טומאה. gram tumah. Okay, same whether it's a Jew or a non-Jew
if he's going to do it בטומאה. b'tumah. Okay, why can't you
be בוצר? botzer? Because here's the point. Even though it's already טמא
tamei and even forget the יין, yayin, it's not a problem about
סתם יינם, stam yaynam, it's a Jew. The Jew himself... You mean
why can't you be דורך, dorekh, right? Why can't you be דורך,
dorekh, excuse me. The Jew himself, this is the guy, he did
an עבירה, aveira, he did and is doing an עבירה. aveira. What
עבירה aveira is he doing, the Jew?
Okay, if he's a Jew,
okay, is the עבירה aveira he's
doing is he's being מטמא טהרות בארץ
ישראל.
metamei taharos
b'eretz yisrael.
Okay, so then a non-Jew doesn't, it's not an עבירה aveira for
a non-Jew. For a Jew it's an עבירה. aveira. So here's the
interesting thing. Even though the עבירה aveira was already done, the stuff
was already טמא, tamei, which is why you're allowed to do it
if you're doing it with a non-Jew because it's already טמא, tamei,
since for the Jew the stomping was an עבירה aveira and now
he's continuing to stomp but the stomping was the עבירה, aveira, for
you to join in you're being מסייע לידי עוברי עבירה. mesayei l'yedei
overei aveira. This is a very important principle because מסייע לידי עוברי
עבירה mesayei l'yedei overei aveira has nothing to do with enabling. You
did not enable. Not only did you not enable, the עבירה aveira
was done. Okay? But the but the act of the עבירה aveira
is still ongoing and you're joining in with him, so that seems
to be like you're
supporting him in the עבירה.
aveira. Now there's different ways of reading it. Is the problem that
you seem to be condoning it and supporting him and you know
and
so on, giving him
יישר כח, yashar koyach, or is the problem that then the עבירה
aveira also attaches to you, right? Is the problem him or is
the problem you? But either way, okay. Now, for example, תוספות Tosfos
says, well let me get to the end of the משנה mishna
and then I'll tell you what תוספות Tosfos says. Now, אבל מוליכין
עמו חביות לגת ומביאין עמו מן הגת.
aval molikhin imo chaviyos l'gat
u'mevin imo min hagat. You can bring barrels to here before the
whole process starts, okay you can bring barrels, and after the process
is over you can bring the barrels, you know, whatever, you can
sort of... you know, so you can do stuff before and you
can do stuff after, you just can't do stuff during. So it's
very sort of formalistically explained. You could have said if the problem
is that I seem to be showing my support, I shouldn't be
able to do anything because it seems like I'm okay with it.
But the rabbis were like lived in the real world and they
realized like you can't restrict stuff that much. Okay, and they said
no, you just can't do the act itself. Okay, you can do
the act before and you can do the act after. Now, תוספות
Tosfos actually, there's some תוספותים Tosfosim that feel that even the before
might not be okay. Okay, we'll get to that later. He explains
the משנה mishna a little bit differently. Okay, I think even רש"י,
Rashi, let me just check רש"י Rashi what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י
Rashi says: מוליכין עמו חביות ריקנות לגת ומביאין עמו חביות מלאות מן
הגת דאין כאן עבירה דמיאחד שנטמא בגת מותר ליתן הי הן בחביות
טמאות. molikhin imo chaviyos reikanos l'gat u'mevin imo chaviyos mlei'os min hagat
d'ein kan aveira d'mi'achad shenitmah bagat mutar litten hey hen b'chaviyos tmeios.
Yeah, it's not clear, okay, whether the bringing the empty barrels occurs
chronologically earlier or after the whole thing is stomped, okay, so it's
all stomped, now you bring the barrels empty, right, and then you
fill them up and then you take them away filled, but it
could be that all of this is after, right? Do people understand?
Like you bring the empty barrels after, you don't necessarily bring them
before. So there's an interesting question whether the stuff leading up to
it is also called מסייע. mesayei. Okay, רש"י, Rashi, this is a
big debate between רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosfos. You can't do בצירה,
betzirah, we said the reason of בצירה betzirah is גרם טומאה. gram
tumah. But maybe another reason you can't do בצירה betzirah is because
of מסייע. mesayei. It could be that the stuff leading up is
מסייע. mesayei. That's רש"י Rashi says no, it's only during. תוספות Tosfos
seems to say even the stuff leading up is מסייע. mesayei. But
as soon as the act is done and now it's a new
act and it's all in the past, it's no longer מסייע. mesayei.
But there's an interesting debate whether this period is, this period is
definitely מסייע, mesayei, this period is... not because it's all in the
past. מסייע, Mesayea, the עבירה aveira is past, and the question is,
is this מסייע, Mesayea, where the עבירה aveira is in the future,
but it's not during. And that seems to be a debate of
רש״י Rashi and תוספות. Tosfos. Okay, so, so that for example, תוספות
Tosfos says, let's say the גת gat itself was טמא. tamei. And
let's say by putting the grapes into the גת, gat, the grapes
already became טמא tamei the moment they were put. Then you'd be
able to stomp with a non-Jew. Because then the act of making
them טמא tamei was the putting, and the stomping is a different
act. Okay, so once it's in the past, anything but anything that's
a new act is permissible. So here though, even though he already
stomped and he already made them טמא, tamei, since the act is
the same act that made them טמא, tamei, that's the problem of
מסייע. Mesayea. It's very important for other areas of הלכה halacha of
what constitutes מסייע ידי עוברי עבירה, Mesayea yedei overei aveira, right? How
could the grapes become טמא? tamei? What? I mean, I understand the
grapes... there's juice still on the bottom that touches it. Okay. So
now, נחתום שהוא עושה בטומאה, Nachtom shehu oseh betuma, similarly if a
baker is doing בטומאה, betuma, לא לשין ולא עורכין עמו, lo lashin
velo orchin imo, you cannot knead the dough or put it in
the... like you know, in the... what's עורך? orech? Like put it
in the... set it on the pans? Yeah, set it in the
pans, like in you know, in the molds. Okay. אבל מוליכין עמו
פת לפלטר, Aval molichin imo pas lepalter, you can bring it to
the פלטר. palter. Now who is the פלטר? palter? Very another interesting
debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos that's also relevant for drawing
the lines here. רש״י Rashi says the פלטר palter is the baker,
meaning the guy who actually puts it in the oven. And you're
the one who actually, so kneading the dough is the same act
of making it טמא, tamei, that's when it becomes טמא. tamei. So
the kneading and the shaping, that's all seen as the same act.
Putting it in the oven is a new act and that you're
allowed to do. Okay. תוספות Tosfos says no, putting it in the
oven is part of the same process. So who's the פלטר palter
for תוספות? Tosfos? For תוספות, Tosfos, the פלטר palter is the retailer.
Okay, after the bread is already baked, you're allowed to bring it
to the retailer and the retailer will now sell it and so
on. Okay, so for that, so it's an interesting question how do
you define the... you know, when is this process done? The טומאה
tuma happened as soon as the guy touched it. But any continued
kneading and shaping is all seen as the same process. Is baking
seen as the same process or is that a new one? Personally,
I... to me רש״י Rashi makes a lot more sense, that baking
is a new process, okay? The act of touching it and becoming
טמא tamei is the kneading and the shaping. But that's an interesting
debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות, Tosfos, when is it considered to
be a new act. So this is an important principle of מסייע
Mesayea and what is the scope of מסייע. Mesayea.
Okay, used in a lot of
תשובות, tshuvos, this discussion for things that have nothing to do with
wine or food. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, יין כיון שהתחיל להימשך עושה יין
נסך. Yayin keivan shehischil lehimallech oseh yayin nesech. He says, not like
this. As soon as the wine begins to be drawn out, it
becomes יין נסך yayin nesech even before it hits the בור. bor.
Seems to disagree with our משנה. Mishnah. תנן, Tnan, let's look at
our משנה. Mishnah. לוקחין גת בעוטה מן העובד כוכבים, Lokchin gat be'uta
min ha'oved kochavim, you can get a stomped, you know, גת. gat.
How do they translate the word גת? gat? What, what is it?
Like a not threshing floor, whatever it is. What? Press, I guess,
press from the non-Jew. ואף על פי שנטל בידו ונתן לתפוח, Ve'af
al pi shenatal beyado venatan latapuach, even though you're now going to
move it or whatever. So אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, בגת
פקוקה ומלאה. Begat pkuka umle'ah. It's talking about that it is full
and it is stopped up, okay, and now we're going to... meaning
nothing has come out of it yet. I'm going to get back
in a minute to the word full. Okay, so whatever, the stuff
is here, it's totally full, nothing has seeped out of it yet.
Okay. The problem is that it says even after it started coming
down at the end of the משנה. Mishnah. תא שמע, Ta shema,
ואינו עושה יין נסך עד שירד לבור. ve'eino oseh yayin nesech ad
sheyered labor. Okay, so it seems like only when it goes down.
הכא נמי בגת פקוקה ומלאה. Hacha nami begat pkuka umle'ah. What we
mean is until you remove, you know, the stopper, it's not יין
נסך. yayin nesech. But okay, it sounds like so once it starts
going down it'll be a problem. תא שמע, Ta shema, ירד לבור
מה שבבור אסור והשאר מותר. Yared labor ma shebabor asur vehashar mutar.
I mean, it's funny, he could have started with that. It says
only once it's down here is it a problem. That sounds very
clearly that the stuff here is not a problem. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara concedes you're right. This is actually a different teaching
than our משנה. Mishnah. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, לא קשיא
כאן במשנה ראשונה כאן במשנה אחרונה. lo kashya kan bemishna rishona kan
bemishna achrona. It's a question about the first... an earlier משנה Mishnah
or the later משנה. Mishnah. דתניא, Detanya, we learn in a ברייתא.
Braisa. בראשונה היו אומרים בבד, Berishona hayu omrim bevad, ואין בוצרין עם
העובד כוכבים בגת, ve'ein botzrin im ha'oved kochavim begat, שאסור לגרום טומאה
לחולין שבארץ ישראל. she'asur ligrom tuma lechulin shebe'eretz yisrael. So this is
the בד, bad, you don't... you're not בוצרין botzrin because you can't
bring about טומאה. tuma. Okay, ואין דורכין עם ישראל, ve'ein dorchin im
Yisrael, you can't stomp with a ישראל Yisrael because that's why? And
now it says explicitly, שעושה פירותיו בטומאה שאסור לסייע ידי עוברי עבירה,
she'oseh peirotav betuma she'asur lesayea yedei overei aveira, okay, אבל דורכין עם
עובד כוכבים בגת, aval dorchin im oved kochavim begat, you can be
דורך. doreich. Why? And ולא חיישינן velo chashinan לרב הונא leRav Huna
because here's the thing, when you're being דורך doreich בגת, begat, okay,
okay, that why don't we, why aren't we concerned that the juice
is already יין yayin and therefore you're doing עבודה, avodah, you're being
נשכר עם איסורי הנאה? niscar im issurei hana'ah? Okay, so why are
you allowed to do this? Only because we're not, only if we
don't rule like רב הונא, Rav Huna, and we actually say that
this is not yet יין. yayin. So that's the early משנה. mishnah.
The early משנה mishnah is what we just described and this isn't
יין yayin and that's why you're allowed to do it with the
non-Jew. So the גמרא's Gemara gloss is ולא חיישינן velo chashinan לרב
הונא, leRav Huna, but the rest of the ברייתא, Baraita, ולא חיישינן
velo chashinan לרב הונא leRav Huna is the גמרא's Gemara gloss, this
is not yet considered to be יין. yayin. Okay. So here רש"י
Rashi gave a reason about עוברי עבירה. overei aveirah. Right. מסייע ידי
עוברי עבירה. mesayeia yedei overei aveirah. Exactly. It's very nice, it spells
out the reason of our משנה, mishnah, and לגרום טומאה. ligrom tumah.
It very nicely clarifies our משנה. mishnah. וחזרו לומר. vachazru lomar. Now
our גרסא girsa is דבד, divad, but it should be probably דבב,
divav, which is what the ב"ח Bach switches it to. אין דורכין,
ein dorchin, that's a ד, dalet, עם עובדי כוכבים im ovdei kochavim
בגת. begat. Okay, we actually say no, I mean it's a little
confusing, whatever, which, you know, how you're supposed to remember them because
any letter could mean anyone. But anyway, you can't do this. Why
can't you do this? משום דרב הונא, mishum deRav Huna, because this
is already considered to be, once the juice starts coming out, it's
already considered to be יין yayin and therefore you're being נשכר באיסורי
הנאה. niscar be'issurei hana'ah. So that's אסור. assur. Okay, we reversed it,
that's אסור, assur, but guess what? Now we're going to make something
that was אסור assur מותר. mutar. ואין בוצרין עם ישראל שעושה פירות
בטומאה. ve'ein botzrin im Yisrael she'oseh peiros betumah. No, you can't, you
continue still can't help a ישראל Yisrael to do בצירה, bitzirah, that
was always אסור, assur, וכל שכן שאין דורכין, vechol shekein she'ein dorchin,
and you can't do דורכין. dorchin. Why? Okay, presumably because that's, I
don't know, מסייע ידי עוברי עבירה, mesayeia yedei overei aveirah, גרם טומאה.
gram tumah. But here's the problem, we're going to have to go
back to this, אבל בוצרין עם עובדי כוכבים בגת. aval botzrin im
ovdei kochavim begat. Now we're telling you you can do help him
do בצירה. bitzirah. Why? Here you can't help him because it's already
איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, it's already יין. yayin. Why can you help
him here? Isn't that a problem about גרם טומאה? gram tumah? So
it says, אבל בוצרין aval botzrin why? שמותר לגרום טומאה לחולין שבארץ
ישראל. shemutar ligrom tumah lechulin shebe'eretz Yisrael. They switched it. Okay, they
originally they said you can't be גורם טומאה gorem tumah but it
isn't yet יין. yayin. All right. And then they switched it to
say it is יין, yayin, so don't do this, but you can
be גורם טומאה gorem tumah so you can go ahead and do
that. So now the point is, okay, then if you could be
גורם טומאה gorem tumah why can't you do all this stuff with
a ישראל? Yisrael? Why can't you do this with a ישראל? Yisrael?
So the answer is, as רש"י Rashi points out, גורם טומאה gorem
tumah is a problem even by stuff like I said before that
will never be תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros. We just don't want stuff
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to become טמא. tamei. Okay, food at
least. But if it's owned by a ישראל, Yisrael, the problem is
that you are making stuff that could have been given to a
כהן, kohen, the תרומה terumah and the חלה challah and whatever, you're
making it טמא tamei and you're taking it away from being able
to be given to a כהן. kohen. So that's a new problem.
If you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, he says three lines
down from the top, אבל ישראל טבולים הם לתרומה ואסור לגרום טומאה
לתרומה דכתיב ואני נתתי את משמרת תרומותי בשתי תרומות הכתוב מדבר. aval
Yisrael tevulin heim leterumah ve'assur ligrom tumah leterumah deketiv va'ani nasati es
mishmeres terumosai bishtei terumos haksiv medabeir. So you can't, if it's a
Jew, why can't you do this? This you can't do because of
גורם טומאה לתרומה gorem tumah leterumah specifically, and this you can't do
because of like מסייע. mesayeia. All right. So if it's a Jew
you can't do this because it's still a problem. It's a problem
because it's because it's because it will be something that will become
תרומה. terumah. But if it's a non-Jew, there's no problem of גרם
טומאה, gram tumah, that's okay. This is a problem because of because
of נשכר באיסורי הנאה. niscar be'issurei hana'ah. All right. Pretty clear to
people? Well, all right, so I want to say two things. First
of all, well why isn't it also a problem of מסייע לעוברי
עבירה? mesayeia le'overei aveirah? I mean, isn't he going to use it
for יין נסך? yayin nesech? יין נסך yayin nesech is an עבירה
aveirah for a non-Jew or it isn't? יין נסך, yayin nesech, it's
it's it's לעבודת כוכבים, le'avodas kochavim, no? סתם יינם. stam yaynam. Okay,
we're not going to assume that. Now, for now here's two interesting
final points about this. Number one is the idea that if it
is אסור assur to make something that is, you know, going to
be תרומה terumah טמא, tamei, so why is this אסור? assur? So
presumably it's אסור assur because of גרם טומאת תרומה, gram tumas terumah,
not סתם גרם טומאה, stam gram tumah, גרם טומאת תרומה. gram tumas
terumah. That's why this is אסור assur with a Jew and this
is אסור assur because of מסייע. mesayeia. Okay, even though the Jew
already made it טמא, tamei, you're continuing the process. תוספות Tosafos however
says this is also מסייע. mesayeia. So this is where תוספות Tosafos
actually says that the בצירה bitzirah is part of the מסייע, mesayeia,
רש"י Rashi disagrees. רש"י Rashi says מסייע mesayeia is only during, תוספות
Tosafos says the מסייע mesayeia is leading up to, leading up as
well. That's point number one. Point number two, there's a big תוספות
Tosafos and this big תוספות Tosafos wants to know, even when the
גמרא Gemara says משנה אחרונה, mishnah achronah, when is this wine considered
to be wine? When is it considered to be נמשך? nimshach? Okay.
And תוספות Tosafos has two possibilities. One possibility is is that it
has to actually sort of go out a little bit from this
thing. Now of course it's not exactly clear where it's going out
there, but תוספות Tosafos but תוספות Tosafos sort of says what would
happen if, he assumes... This gets to the question of the גרסא
*girsa* of it's full. Okay? Why did the ברייתא *braita* before say
it was full? All right? Because remember it said it was a
full thing? Because if it weren't full, what you could have is
you could have your grapes here and you could have a little
spot in the middle where some of it is puddling up. Okay?
So opposed to it all being here trapped in the middle, if
it's not full it could puddle a little bit and that would
already be משיכה *meshicha*. Okay? So that's one way he reads it,
that it's משיכה *meshicha* once it already puddles in the middle, but
another explanation is even that is not משיכה *meshicha* until it actually
leaves the thing. Now I'm not exactly clear then why how he
explains with the stomping and so on because it hasn't left it
yet unless the point was what it was stopped up, you know,
maybe if it was undone and then the stuff started flowing down
but you're still stomping here, you're not stomping there. Anyway, the big
נפקא מינא *nafka mina* for תוספות *Tosafot* was their contemporary practice with
wine, because they would have not a גת *gat*, they would have
these narrow barrels, I mean I don't know so narrow, okay, and
they would be pretty full, okay, and the question was could they
go ahead and stomp with the non-Jews because it wouldn't be considered
that there would be משיכה *meshicha* or not. If you were considered
about this pooling in the middle on the floor, then that might
be a case of משיכה *meshicha* and it would be a problem.
But if it would actually have to leave, it would not be
a problem. So that was the big question whether they could do
this with non-Jews at what stage does it considered to be משיכה
*meshicha*. So if you take a look at this big תוספות *Tosafot*,
let's just try to pull out for you one or two interesting
lines. He says like this, he says, we'll start from the beginning.
אמר רב הונא *Amar Rav Huna*, פירוש הקונטרס שהגת עשויה במדרון ומשעה
שהוא נמשך מצד העליון לצד התחתון קרי יין *Peirush HaKuntres shehagat asuya
bemidron umishaa shehu nimshach mitzad haelyon letzad hatachton karei yayin*. In an
angle and as soon as it starts being. סמך נמי פירש בגת
פקוקה מלאה ולא נמשך היין ולא זז ממקומו *somach nami peirush begat
pekuka meleah velo nimshach hayayin velo zaz mimkomo*. The wine didn't move
at all, it totally stayed where it was. אלא מקום שנשחק שמה
עמד במקום שיפול העץ שם יהא *ela makom shenishchak shama amad bemakom
sheyipol haetz sham yehei*. נראה מתוך פירושה דאפילו בגת עצמה אם פינה
החרצנים אילך ואילך ונשאר היין לצד אחד הוה התחיל לימשך *nira mitoch
peirushah deafilu begat atzmah im pina hachartzanim ilech veilech venishar hayayin letzad
echad hava hitchil limashech*. If you just pushed them all one side
and they collected even in the same container, that would be considered
משיכה *meshicha*. ודינא נמי בגיגיות שלנו שדורכים בהם וכן פירש הרשב"ם בשם
רש"י Rashi, *vedina nami begagiyot shelanu shedorchim bahem vechein peirush HaRashbam beshem
Rashi*. Okay, then that would mean it would be a problem even
our barrels if the if it collected if there was a little
puddling inside the barrel that would be a problem. Okay, and then
he so goes on and on and on and then he says
like this for רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam, *Rabbenu Tam*, if you look
at the last line of the middle-sized lines, okay, פירוש שהתחיל לימשך
שהתחיל לקלח מן הגת קודם שיירד לבור *peirush shehitchil limashech shehitchil lekaleach
min hagat kodem sheyeired labor*, that it actually started moving away. Okay,
that's the problem. Okay, so I guess this would only be a
problem even maybe there weren't two stages, I don't know if this
went straight into the בור *bor* whatever, but anyway, maybe this would
only be a problem when it started flowing. Of course then you'd
have to say that once that flowing started, it makes everything in
here problem as well, I don't know exactly anyway, whatever. But he
says it's only considered it's only considered משיכה *meshicha*, you know, it's
נמשך *nimshach* after it actually leaves the container itself. ופריך תנן לא
כגספותא אף על פי שופים *upareiich tnan lo kegasputa af pi shevafim*
whatever and he goes on and says like this. ופירושו *upeirusho*, if
you look three lines down in the wide lines, ואם פינה הענבים
אילך ואילך ונשאר היין בגומא באמצע הגיגית אין כאן המשכה *veim pina
haanavim ilech veilech venishar hayayin beguma beemtza hagigit ein kan hamshacha*. If
it puddles in the middle it's not a problem, it's only a
problem if it leaves the barrel. כיון שלא הניח שם גרגותני לסיין
היין *keivan shelo hiniach sham gargutani lesayen hayayin*. אבל אם משך היין
מן הגיגית דרך הברז *aval im mashach hayayin min hagagit derech habaraz*
and then he talks about different types of scenarios about taking it
out etc. So that becomes the whole question about whether they can
do this with the non-Jews while it's in the same barrel. And
then if you jump down he says like this, near the bottom
he says, okay, you see where it says ומאוד *umaod*, it's like
seven lines above the word אין *ein*, above the next תוספות *Tosafot*.
He says like this, he says, ומאוד יש להחמיר בצידי המשכה והמחמיר
לתת צדין על הגיגית ולכרוך הגיגית ולחותמה תבא עליו ברכה *umaod yesh
lehachmir betzidei hamshacha vehamachmir latet tzedin al hagagit velichrot hagigit ulechosma tavon
alav bracha*. Okay, you have to be very careful because he was
also concerned, the other concern was also that, you know, when they
were processing the wine would a non-Jew take some wine from a
different barrel and mix it into your barrel? So even if you
assume that your barrel was okay because the wine hadn't left it,
right? But how do you know all the wine that's in your
barrel was the original wine and wasn't added from some other barrel?
So they spoke about putting seals on it and covers on it
and the whole thing. And then he says like this, ויש היו
רוצים למצוא חן בעיני עובדי כוכבים והיו עובדי כוכבים דורכים עמהם בגיגיות
קודם המשכה *Veyesh hayu rotzim limtzo chen beinei ovdei kochavim vehayu ovdei
kochavim dorchim imahem begigiyot kodem hamshacha*. Exactly, so they would have them
do it. ושמע רבנו יעקב והקפיד ורצה לנדותם אם לא ישמעו וישובו
ולא יעשו עוד כך כי אולי אסרו לפני... *Veshamar Rabbeinu Yaakov vehikpid
veratza linosom im lo yishmu veyashuvu velo yaasu od kach ki ulai
asru lifnei...* משנה אחרונה דריכה קודם המשכה drichah kodem hamshachah אטו אחר
המשכה atu achar hamshachah אף על גב דלא גזרינן af al gav
delo gazrinan et cetera, et cetera. So again, one of these great
Tosafists that deals with these contemporary realities, and the big question is,
okay, certainly if it if it's filled and nothing puddles, that's okay,
and that's what he thought the reality was here. According to רש"י,
Rashi, it's possible if it if it puddled in the in the
container, it would be a problem, but he said his reality in
the barrel was was that, you know, actually, well
that's what he wasn't sure, excuse me, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. If
it,
according to רש"י, if it puddled, it was a problem. According to
רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, it's only a problem if it actually left
left the container. So he feels that in his case about these,
you know, these things, A, there's a question does he have to
be concerned about puddling, maybe yes, but certainly he doesn't seem to
be concerned about it leaving the container, so that was the question
about can you have a non-Jew participate, because according to at least
especially like רבנו תם, it would not have left the container and
it wouldn't yet be a problem, okay? And then he deals with
like a whole range of other possible issues and scenarios, but anyway,
here is the application of our discussion to his very practical scenario.
All right, we continue tomorrow. יישר כח. Yasher koach. Rabbi, when do
you feel